A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial records, Counsel's Office, Series 10 FA358
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Michael Whiteman, 1963-1974; 4; 80 Document Box(es)
  The files in this subseries are arranged by broad subject headings, and thereunder the folder order is mostly chronological but somewhat arbitrary.
  Michael Whiteman was born in New York, New York, and grew up near Great Neck on Long Island. He graduated magna cum laude from Harvard College and cum laude from Harvard Law School. After graduation, Mr. Whiteman remained at Harvard for one year as a research assistant to Paul A. Freund, the Carl M. Loeb University Professor, and as a teaching assistant in general education. In 1963 he joined Governor Rockefeller's staff, serving for ten years in various capacities as detailed above. Upon Governor Rockefeller's resignation in December 1973, Mr. Whiteman served as Counsel to Governor Malcolm Wilson until December 1974. He then became a founding partner of the Albany, New York law firm of Whiteman Osterman & Hanna, where he specializes in energy and telecommunication law, government contracting, corporate law, business professional practices, and governmental ethics.
  This subseries contains a portion of the office files of Michael Whiteman and other members of the office of Counsel to the Governor. They document the official activities of these individuals in the execution of their duties as members of Nelson A. Rockefeller's gubernatorial staff. The actions, decisions, and exchanges of information or points of view documented here occurred in the course of proposing and implementing policies for the Rockefeller administrations and political campaigns. However, unless a document is personally signed by Nelson A. Rockefeller, or is referred to in a document personally signed by him, it should not be assumed that he saw the document or was aware of its existence or substance. Furthermore, researchers should bear in mind that staff files may contain documents or drafts addressed to Rockefeller that were never shown to him.
  This subseries contains a portion of the files of Michael Whiteman (MW) from his years as Confidential Law Assistant (1963-1964), Assistant Counsel (1964-1967), First Assistant Counsel (1967-1971), and Counsel (1971-1973) to Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller of New York. Mr. Whiteman also served as Acting Counsel to the Governor from May through August 1968.
  The files in this subseries remain in the original order in which they were arranged while in active use in Mr. Whiteman's office. There is a broad subject heading to the arrangement, and thereunder the folder order is mostly chronological but somewhat arbitrary. Boxes 1 and 2 contain various studies and statistical and demographic projections that came to Mr. Whiteman at the earliest stages of his government service. Boxes 3 and 4 comprise his chronological files, which were not continued after early 1967. Boxes 5 to 7 contain requests made through the Counsel's Office to the New York State Police Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) for information on prospective government employees. Boxes 8 through 14 are general materials related to various state governmental authorities, including the Niagara Frontier Port Authority, the New York State Atomic Research and Development Authority, the Port of New York Authority, the State Tax Commission, and the State Liquor Authority.
  Boxes 17 to 20 deal with legislation in 1968 and 1969, including the Recodification of the Vehicle and Traffic Law. Boxes 22 to 35 contain papers related to the Governor's Legislative programs between 1969 and 1972. Boxes 39 through 69 deal with state issues that arose during 1969 to 1973. The remaining materials (Boxes 70 to 80) relate to legislation, the 1973 Governor's Legislative Program, and other 1973 issues--most notably the legislation that became known as the Rockefeller Drug Laws. There is only one folder in this subseries (Box 44, Folder 464) on the September 1971 riot at Attica Prison and the ensuing effort by the state to retake control of the prison.
  - General - Office of Transportation - Long-Range Planning Submission, 1966; 3 volumes (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General - New York State Moreland Commission on Alcoholic Beverage Control Law, 1963; 5 papers (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General - Management Survey of New York State Liquor Authority by Division of Budget, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General - Memorandum re Bill to Promote Vocational Education Through Area Centers, ca. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General - Memorandum re Bill to Repeal New York State's Full Crew Laws, ca. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General - Memorandum re Bill to Clarify Bill Creating Metropolitan Commuter Transportation Authority, ca. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General - Memorandum re Bill to Create Public Authority to Improve Commuter Transportation in New York City, ca. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General - Education - Cultural Education - Projections, ca. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General - Education - Research and Evaluation - Projections, ca. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General - Education - Higher and Professional Education - Projections, ca. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General - Education - Regents Examination and Scholarship Center - Projections, ca. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General - Education - Educational Finance and Management Services - Projections, ca. 1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - General - Education - Elementary and Secondary Education - Projections, ca. 1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - General - Education - Center on Innovation in Education - Projections, ca. 1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - General - Education - Vocational Rehabilitation, ca. 1966 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - General - Education - Business Management and Personnel, ca. 1966 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - General - Public Service Commission Programs, ca. 1967 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Utilities Regulation Transportation Regulations Highway - Railroad Crossings Program Administrative Plan Departmental Summary
  - General - Nelson A. Rockefeller Campaign Literature, 1963, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - General - Alcoholic Beverage Control Law, 1963-1965, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Moreland Commission Interim Report, August 30, 1963 Letter of thanks to Whiteman for assisting the Commission's work Moreland Commission Report (3 vols.), 1966
  - General - State Science and Technology Foundation Meeting Minutes, September 28, 1966, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - General - Power Authority Issue (Nuclear Development), 1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - General - Judiciary - Terms and Birthdates, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - General - Addresses of New York State Departments, Agencies, Organizations, ca. 1962 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - General - Reading File (Chronological) - Correspondence, September-December 1963 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - General - Reading File (Chronological) - Correspondence, January-March 1964 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - General - Reading File (Chronological) - Correspondence, April-June 1964 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - General - Reading File (Chronological) - Correspondence, July-September 1964 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - General - Reading File (Chronological) - Correspondence, October-December 1964 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - General - Reading File (Chronological) - Correspondence, January-March 1965 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - General - Reading File (Chronological) - Correspondence, April-June 1965 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - General - Reading File (Chronological) - Correspondence, July-September 1965 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - General - Reading File (Chronological) - Correspondence, October-December 1965 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - General - Reading File (Chronological) - Correspondence, January-March 1966 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - General - Reading File (Chronological) - Correspondence, April-June 1966 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - General - Reading File (Chronological) - Correspondence, July-September 1966 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - General - Reading File (Chronological) - Correspondence, October-December 1966 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - General - Reading File (Chronological) - Correspondence, January-March 1967 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests - Moreland Commission on Alcoholic Beverage Control Law, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests, January-February 1962 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests, March-April 1962 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests, May-June 1962 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests, July-September 1962 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests, October-December 1962 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests, January-February 1963 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests, March-June 1963 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests, July-December 1963 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests, January-June 1964 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests, July-December 1964 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests, January-March 1965 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests, March-June 1965 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests, July-September 1965 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests, October-December 1965 (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests, January-March 1967 (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests, April-May 1967 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests, June-August 1967 (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - General - Bureau of Criminal Investigation (BCI) Requests, September-December 1967 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - General - Niagara Frontier Port Authority, 1963-1964 (Box 8, Folder 57)
    Minutes Special meetings, June 25, 1963, July 8, 1963 Regular meeting, November 9, 1964
  - General - Niagara Frontier Port Authority, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 58)
    Minutes, April 12, 1965, June 14, 1965, July 12, 1965
  - General - Niagara Frontier Port Authority, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 59)
    Minutes, August 3, 1965, August 27, 1965, October 4, 1965, November 8, 1965
  - General - Niagara Frontier Port Authority, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 60)
    Minutes, December 13, 1965, December 22, 1965 Annual budget for year ending March 31, 1966
  - General - New York State Atomic Research and Development Agency, 1963-1964 (Box 9, Folder 61)
    Minutes, September 18, 1963, December 11, 1963 Second annual meeting, January 24, 1964, January 28, 1964, February 19, 1964
  - General - New York State Atomic Research and Development Agency, 1964-1965 (Box 9, Folder 62)
    Minutes, February 28, 1964, April 16, 1964, May 25, 1965, June 22, 1965
  - General - Departmental Reports - First Quarter, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 63)
    Office of Atomic Development, April 22, 1963 Department of Motor Vehicles, April 22, 1963 Insurance Department, April 15, 1963 Public Service Commission, April 15, 1963 Department of Public Works, April 15, 1963 Office of Transportation, April 15, 1963
  - General - Departmental Reports - Second Quarter, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 64)
    Atomic Development, Insurance, Motor Vehicles, Public Service Commission, Public Works, Transportation
  - General - Departmental Reports - Third Quarter, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 65)
  - General - Departmental Reports - Fourth Quarter, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 66)
    Insurance, Motor Vehicles, Public Service Commission, Public Works, Transportation
  - General - Departmental Reports - First Quarter, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 67)
  - General - Port of New York Authority, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 68)
    By-Laws (corrected to July 1, 1960)
  - General - Port of New York Authority, 1962-1963; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 10, Folder 69)
    Litigation re: constitutionality of World Trade Center, briefs and affidavits in New York State supreme court, appellate division and court of appeals.
  - General - Port of New York Authority, 1962-1963; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 10, Folder 70)
  - General - Port of New York Authority, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 71)
    United States Supreme Court motion to dismiss.
  - General - Port of New York Authority, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 72)
    Report of special New Jersey state investigating committee.
  - General - Atomic Research and Development Authority, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 73)
    1963 annual Report, correspondence, lease to Nuclear Fuel Services, Incorporated; facilities contract with Nuclear Fuel Services, Incorporated.
  - General - Department of Motor Vehicles - Report to Governor, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 74)
  - General - New York State Police Appropriation Request Fiscal 1968-1969, Folder 1 of 3 (Box 10, Folder 75)
  - General - New York State Police Budget Request Fiscal 1968-1969, Folder 2 of 3 (Box 11, Folder 76)
  - General - New York State Police Budget Request Fiscal 1968-1969, Folder 3 of 3 (Box 11, Folder 77)
  - General - Niagara Frontier Port Authority - Minutes, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 78)
    Special meeting, August 27, 1962 Regular meetings, September 10, 1962 and October 15, 1962 Special meeting, November 7, 1962 Regular meetings, November 20, 1962 and December 10, 1962
  - General - Niagara Frontier Port Authority - Minutes, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 79)
    Meetings, January 14, 1963, February 11, 1963, March 11, 1963, May 20, 1963, June 14, 1963, July 8, 1963, August 5, 1963.
  - General - Niagara Frontier Port Authority - Minutes, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 80)
    Meetings, August 15, 1963, September 9, 1963, October 10, 1963, October 28, 1963, November 18, 1963, December 9, 1963, December 20, 1963.
  - General - Niagara Frontier Port Authority - Minutes, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 81)
    Meetings, January 13, January 24, February 10, March 9, April 20, 1964
  - General - Niagara Frontier Port Authority - Minutes, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 82)
    Meetings, May 11, June 8, July 13, August 17, September 14, October 13, December 14, 1964
  - General - Niagara Frontier Port Authority - Minutes, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 83)
    Minutes, January 11, January 25, February 8, February 9, March 8, March 17, April 14, May 3, 1965 Conflict of interest, May 31, 1967 By-laws, 1963
  - General - State Liquor Authority, 1962-1963 (Box 12, Folder 84)
    Miscellaneous, press releases, correspondence, November 1962-December 1963.
  - General - State Liquor Authority, 1964-1966 (Box 12, Folder 85)
    Miscellaneous, press releases, correspondence, January 1964-November 1966.
  - General - State Tax Commission, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 86)
    Investigation, indictment, resignation of Walter Conlon, State Tax Commission.
  - General - State Tax Commission - Conlon Investigation, September 1967 (Box 12, Folder 87)
    Newsclippings.
  - General - State Tax Commission - Conlon Investigation, October-December 1967 (Box 12, Folder 88)
  - General - Criminal Justice, March-April 1968 (Box 13, Folder 89)
    Newsclippings and handwritten notes on District Attorney of Erie County firing of black female assistant district attorney.
  - General - Onondaga District Attorney, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 90)
    Resignation of Edward Gerber over membership in Minuteman organization.
  - General - International Business Machines (IBM) Lease (Equipment), 1966 (Box 13, Folder 91)
    Correspondence on investigation of alleged improper conduct by unnamed state employee - case closed.
  - General - Significant Case - Nebro Johnson, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 92)
    Correspondence on request for clemency.
  - General - Special Case - L. Judson Morhouse, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 93)
    Correspondence on status of case on appeal.
  - General - Special Investigations, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 94)
    Police dog license fee exemption bill.
  - General - Special Investigations, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 95)
    Maislin Brothers training - overlord fines.
  - General - Special Investigations, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 96)
    Dr. Mathen - Interfaith Hospital, building seizure for drug addiction rehab.
  - General - Special Investigations, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 97)
    Sam McDowell case - Albany civil rights leader, excessive jail term sentence for assault.
  - General - Criminal Justice - Grand Jury, 1966-1967 (Box 13, Folder 98)
    New York County painting contractors investigation.
  - General - Special Investigations, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 99)
    Oneonta Ralston-Purina strike.
  - General - Criminal Justice - Superession of District Attorneys, 1965-1969 (Box 13, Folder 100)
    Research and memos on supersession, order of supersession re: Erie County Post Office garage (1965), request for supersession by Mayor of Watertown (1966), request for supersession of Onondaga County District Attorney by Donald Maloney who was indicted by Onondaga grand jury (1966), comptroller's report of Schenectady Police Court and memo to Schenectady District Attorney not to proceed (1967), order of supersession in Hamilton County made at request of Hamilton County District Attorney (1969).
  - General - State Liquor Authority, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 101)
    Legislative proposals re: licensing at World's Fair, off-premises licensing.
  - General - State Liquor Authority, 1964-1966 (Box 13, Folder 102)
    Minimum drinking age, studies, Nelson A. Rockefeller press releases, memos.
  - General - State Liquor Authority, 1963-1964 (Box 13, Folder 103)
    Moreland Act Commission: revision of Alcoholic Beverage Control Law, Nelson A. Rockefeller press releases, correspondence, news articles.
  - General - State Liquor Authority, 1964-1965 (Box 13, Folder 104)
    Package store removals, copies of pleadings and briefs in "removal" proceedings.
  - General - State Liquor Authority, 1963-1965 (Box 13, Folder 105)
    Quarterly reports.
  - General - State Liquor Authority, 1964, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 106)
    Tourist imports of alcoholic beverages: correspondence, reports, drafts of bills restricting importation.
  - General - State Liquor Authority, 1966 (Box 14, Folder 107)
    Alcoholic Beverage Control Law Section 101-b (requires an affirmation that the price of liquor to wholesalers is no higher than the lowest price to any wholesaler in the United States) Petition by Seagrams and State Liquor Authority to allow sales at prices above those allowed by Section 101-b, correspondence memos, reports.
  - General - State Liquor Authority, 1965 (Box 14, Folder 108)
    Copies of pleading and discussions in Seagrams case.
  - General - State Liquor Authority (Box 14, Folder 109)
    Post-trial memorandum and proposed findings in "Victor Fischel & Company, Incorporated vs. R. H. Macy & Company, Incorporated" -- action brought by Fisher alleging price cutting by Macy after November 16, 1964 when State Liquor Authority no longer enforced fixed prices.
  - General - State Liquor Authority, 1964-1965, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 110)
    Miscellaneous correspondence and memos.
  - Office of Local Government - 1969 Departmental Legislation (Box 15, Folder 111)
  - Office of Local Government - 1969 Legislative Proposals (Box 15, Folder 112)
    1969 Legislative proposal No. 1, In-Service Training 1969 Legislative proposal No. 2, Annexation of Territory 1969 Legislative proposal No. 3, Environmental Protection 1969 Legislative proposal No. 9, Dissolution of Special Improvements Districts 1969 Legislative proposal, State Aid for Intermunicipal Cooperative Studies
  - Office of Local Government - Ambulances - Legislation, Crew Requirements, 1966 (Box 15, Folder 113)
  - Office of Local Government - Budget Material, 1963-1964, 1964-1965 (Box 15, Folder 114)
  - Office of Local Government - Home Rule Message, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 115)
  - Office of Local Government - Conflicts of Interests Memo (Rockland County), 1968 (Box 15, Folder 116)
  - Office of Local Government - Constitutional Convention - Proposed Office of Local Government (OLG) Article, 1967 (Box 15, Folder 117)
  - Office of Local Government - Conference of Mayors - Legislative Program, 1966 (Box 15, Folder 118)
  - Office of Local Government - Demonstration Cities Program, 1967 (Box 15, Folder 119)
  - Office of Local Government - Equalization and Assessment - Age Exemption, 1966 (Box 15, Folder 120)
  - Office of Local Government - Equalization and Assessment - Veterans Exemption, 1967 (Box 15, Folder 121)
  - Office of Local Government - Federal Funds - Correspondence - Demonstration Cities Fund, 1967 (Box 15, Folder 122)
  - Office of Local Government - Equalization and Assessment - Syracuse Airport, 1967 (Box 15, Folder 123)
  - Office of Local Government - "Local Assistance" Expenditures, 1966 (Box 15, Folder 124)
  - Office of Local Government - Municipal Tort Liability Legislation (Proposals), 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 125)
  - Office of Local Government (OLG) Press Releases, 1968; Budget Presentation, 1961-1968 (Box 15, Folder 126)
  - Office of Local Government - Fire Legislation, 1966 (Box 15, Folder 127)
  - Office of Local Government - Fire Districts, 1967 (Box 15, Folder 128)
  - Office of Local Government - Fire Protection: Cornell, Stony Brook; Division of Fire Safety Services Brochure (1968), 1966 (Box 15, Folder 129)
  - Office of Local Government - Hudson River Lands - Assessment of Lands Under Hudson River, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 130)
  - Office of Local Government - Legal Services for the Poor Program Guides, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 131)
  - Office of Local Government - Local Government - Rockland County, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 132)
    Complaint about possible conflict of interest with county officials acting as sewer district attorneys.
  - Office of Local Government - Local Government - Towns - Digest of Laws, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 133)
  - Office of Local Government - Local Reapportionment - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 134)
  - Office of Local Government - Training for Local Officials - Nelson A. Rockefeller News Release, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 135)
  - Office of Local Government - Population Survey, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 136)
  - Office of Local Government - Sewage, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 137)
  - Office of Local Government - Urban Field, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 138)
    Defined as "a core area of 300,000" and about 100 miles; report to Director of Budget; paper by Professor Charles Press, Michigan State University: "The Cities within a Great City ...," 1967.
  - Office of Local Government - Volunteer Firemen - Correspondence, 1963-1966 (Box 16, Folder 139)
  - Office of Local Government - Volunteer Firemen's Benevolent Association, 1964 (Box 16, Folder 140)
  - Office of Local Government - Home Rule, 1961-1965 (Box 16, Folder 141)
  - Legislation - Albany Independent Movement (AIM), 1967 (Box 16, Folder 142)
    Correspondence and news clippings re: "Election Fraud" (alleged $5 votes).
  - Legislation - Albany Port District Commission, 1961-1967 (Box 16, Folder 143)
    Issue of confidentiality of Commission files - memos, reports, notes; newspaper articles; legislation; membership of Commission.
  - Legislation - Arts - Ithaca Arts Festival, 1965 (Box 16, Folder 144)
    Proposal to create and fund Arts Festival and Arts Center.
  - Legislation - Association of the Bar, 1963-1967 (Box 17, Folder 145)
    Attempt by Queens County Bar to advise Governor on judicial appointments.
  - Legislation - Bill Jacket Security, 1968 (Box 17, Folder 146)
  - Legislation - Campaign, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 147)
    Press releases, fliers, "Report of 1970 New York City Campaign," Goldberg statements, memo by Lewis Bart Stone.
  - Legislation - Cary Estate, 1968 (Box 17, Folder 148)
    Correspondence: Estate of Mrs. Melbart Cary Jr., granddaughter of Henry Flagler.